Finding Aid for Robert M. Beckley papers, 1958-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert M. Beckley papers 1958-2012 1978-2011
Beckley, Robert Mark, 1934-
2011020 Aa 2
Architect, urban planner, professor and dean of the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning at the University of Michigan, 1987-1997. Records include teaching files, urban design projects in Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Bellevue, Washington; and Lake Oswego, Oregon; work with the Genesee Institute and County Land Bank in Michigan; articles; technical and preparatory drawings.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Papers were received beginning in 1997 (Donor 8616 ). The bulk of the papers were received in April 2011.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Robert Mark Beckley was born in 1934 in Cleveland, Ohio and attended the University of Cincinnati (BS 1959) and the Harvard Graduate School of Design (MA 1961). He joined the University of Michigan faculty as an instructor in 1963 and was promoted to assistant professor in 1965. In 1968 Beckley joined the faculty of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee where he served as chair and acting dean in the School of Architecture and Urban Planning, a program he helped establish. Beckley's professional projects in Milwaukee included assisting in the creation of two urban design centers, one in the African American community and one in the Latino community. He also worked on projects with the City of Milwaukee Economic Development Department investigating infill housing options and the Milwaukee Redevelopment Corporation (MRC) on downtown development.
In 1980, he founded the firm Beckley/Myers Architects with colleague Sherrill Myers. Under Beckley's direction the firm completed urban design plans for the Milwaukee River Walk, the Milwaukee Theater District and the Bellevue Downtown Park in Bellevue, Washington as well as numerous architectural commissions. Beckley left the firm in 1992 to devote full time to academic administration.
In 1987, Beckley returned to the University of Michigan as professor of architecture and urban planning and dean of the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning. Beckley stepped down as dean in 1997 after serving for ten years. He resumed his professional activity and participated in designs for a downtown park in Lake Oswego, Oregon, and the development of urban design guidelines for the State Street Redevelopment Project in Ann Arbor. From 2002 to 2007 he served as a planning consultant to the Genesee County Land Bank and as Executive Vice Chair of the Genesee Institute, an enterprise he helped establish with foundation support that provided planning, research and technical assistance to land banks. In 2009 he was asked to be Chairman of the Board of the Center for Community Progress, a merger of the Genesee Institute and the National Vacant Properties Campaign being funded by the Ford and C.S. Mott Foundations as well as others.
Beckley was made a Fellow of the Urban Design Institute in 1990 and the American Institute of Architects in 1985. His service included terms as President and Treasurer of the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture and an officer on the National Architectural Accrediting Board. He worked on research grants from the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), the U.S. Departments of Housing and Urban Development and Department of Transportation. He also served as Urban Research Scientist while at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Beckley received recognition and awards for design, research and service from the NEA, Progressive Architecture Magazine, the American Institute of Architects, the City of Milwaukee and the Urban Land Institute.
Robert Beckley died in Ann Arbor on May 1, 2015.
The papers of Robert M. Beckley measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1958 to 2012. The bulk of materials are from 1978 to 2011. The collection is comprised of articles, drawings and reports, but little correspondence. It includes theoretical and applied material relating to urban design, created as a student in the University of Cincinnati and in the Harvard University Graduate School of Design, as dean of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, and as private consultant. The papers contain five series: Biographical, Articles, Lectures and Writings, Applied Works, University of Michigan and Genesee Institute and Genesee County Land Bank.
Subjects:
Architecture.; Beckley, Robert M.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning.; Architecture--Designs and plans.; Urban renewal--Wisconsin--Milwaukee.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.2 linear feet, 1961-2011) traces Robert Beckley's career. Included in the series is a curriculum vitae, articles and clippings about Beckley and his work, awards and citations, photographs, and an autobiographical text, "Reflections of a Dean" written in 2011.
  - American Institute of Architects (Box 1)
    - Fellow 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Resignations 2000 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Clippings 1980-1991 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Citations 1961-2006 (Box 1)
    (see also outsized material in Box 4)
  - Biographical (Box 1)
    (includes curriculum vitae)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Reflections of a Dean 2011 (Box 1)
- Articles, Lectures and Writings
  The series Articles, Lectures and Writings (0.4 linear feet, 1966-2012) is a chronologically arranged collection of works authored by Beckley beginning in 1966 with his time as editor of the Michigan Society of Architects Bulletin. The series contains published articles as well as unpublished lectures and statements from art exhibitions.
  - Michigan Society of Architects Bulletin Articles, editorials and graphic material prepared by Robert Beckley while serving as editor, January 1966-March 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Unified Transportation Systems and Future Urban and Regional Development," written with Hub White and Charles N. Ehler 1969 (Box 1)
  - "The Effects of Federal Programs on Housing and the Quality of Life: The Milwaukee Case," 1978 (Box 1)
  - Park West Freeway Corridor 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - "Controversial Public Art: a Symposium" 1983 (Box 1)
  - "Ruins, Constructions and Ambiguous Buildings: a theory," 1981 (Box 1)
  - "The Value and Purpose of the Design Studio in Architectural Education" (Amos Rapoport debate) 1984 (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Architectural Education 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - International Conference on Urban Design "Milwaukee Repertory Theater 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Mobile Dreams" (Mobile Homes) 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Providing a Lung for an Increasingly Congested Bellevue," 1987 (Box 1)
  - "Illegal Houses: Propriety, Tragedy and Comedy," 1989 (Box 1)
  - "The Arcade: a Forgotten Urban Type," 1990 (Box 1)
  - "Making a Public Realm," 1990 (Box 1)
  - "Making Public Places," undated (Box 1)
  - "Collaboration and the Public," 1991 (Box 1)
  - "Flint Michigan and the Cowboy Economy: Deconstructing Flint," 2005 (Box 1)
  - place mark exhibit 2008 (Box 1)
  - Storm exhibit 2009 (Box 1)
  - "Inessential Background" artist statement 2012 (Box 1)
- Applied Works
  The series Applied Works (1.0 linear foot, 1958-2001) is about the making of building plans and urban design work done as a student and as a professional. The series is subdivided into two subseries: Student Work and Professional Work. Student Work contains projects done as an undergraduate at the University of Cincinnati and as a graduate student at Harvard University Graduate School of Design. Some work done with the Cincinnati architectural firm Garber, Tweddell and Wheeler is located within this series.
  - Student Works
    - University of Cincinnati
      - Museum and Library for the Historical and Philosophical Society of Ohio, University of Cincinnati 1957-1958 (Box 1)
      - Youth Camp for the Settlements of the Greater Cincinnati area 1958 (Box 1)
      - Garber, Tweddell and Wheeler 1958-1960 (Box 1)
      - Art Commons, University of Cincinnati, senior thesis 1959 (Box 1)
      - New Town Competition Entry 1959 (Box 1)
        (oversized located in Box 4)
    - Harvard University Graduate School of Design
      - Boston Arts Festival, Harvard Graduate School of Design 1960 (Box 1)
      - Core of a City for 200.000 to be Located between Washington D.C. and Baltimore 1961 (Box 4)
        (oversized)
      - Entry in the 4th annual Ruberoid competition 1962 (Box 1)
        (oversized located in Box)
      - Harvard Graduate School of Design 1960 (Box 1)
      - Multipurpose Exhibition Structure 1961 (Box 4)
      - Residence (Box 1)
      - Science Center for Tulane 1960 (Box 4)
      - Student Chapel, IES Competition (Box 1)
      - Work accomplished with the firm of Garber, Tweddell and Wheeler, architects, Cincinnati (Ohio) 1959-1963 (oversized) (Box 4)
  - Professional Works 1960-2011
    Professional Work illustrates Beckley's private work as an architect, urban designer and consultant. Professional Work is subdivided in four categories: Milwaukee, Wisconsin Projects, Bellevue, Washington Downtown Park, Lake Oswego, Oregon Millennium Park, and Other Projects. The Milwaukee material includes urban infill work as well as several private projects and work done with the firm Beckley and Meyers. Some material relating to teaching and administration at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee is part of this series.
    - Milwaukee, Wisconsin Projects
      - Arena House Frank Lloyd Wright American System Built House 1983-2011 (Box 1)
      - Beckley/Myers/Flad 1986 (Box 1)
      - Leipold House Racine, Wisconsin 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      - Milwaukee Lakefront Design Competition 1980-1983 (Box 1)
      - Milwaukee Redevelopment 1979 (Box 1)
      - Milwaukee Repertory Theater 1983-1993 (Box 1)
      - Milwaukee River Walk 1983-1985, 2002 (Box 1)
      - Milwaukee Theater Facility Impact Study 1981-1983 (Box 1)
      - Mitchell Center 1971-1972 (Box 1)
      - Park East Freeway Corridor Redevelopment Plan 1987 (Box 1)
      - 3232 House, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
      - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Correspondence 1982-1985 (Box 1)
      - Urban Design at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (Box 1)
    - Bellevue, Washington Downtown Park
      - Bellevue Downtown Park 1984-1997 (Box 1)
      - Articles 1987-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Phase I 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Phase II 1984-1996 (Box 2)
      - Phase III 1997 (Box 2)
      - Graphics 1997 (Box 2)
      - Photographs 1997-2001 (Box 2)
    - Lake Oswego, Oregon Millennium Park
      - Plans 1998 (Box 2)
      - Plans 1998-1999 (Box 2)
      - Photographs 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Lake Oswego, Oregon Millennium Park
      - Communications with MacLeod Rekord 1998-1999 (Box 2)
      - Contract for Design Services 1998 (Box 2)
      - Simon Toparovsky's artwork 1999 (Box 2)
      - Slides 1998-2001 (Box 2)
    - Other Projects
      - Chicago Architecture Club (Box 2)
      - Planning System Group, Ann Arbor, Michigan 1967-1970 (Box 2)
      - Saint-John's Unitarian Church, Cincinnati, Ohio 1960, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - State Street Development Project, Ann Arbor, Michigan 2000 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series (0.8 linear feet, 1985-2010) includes documentation on Beckley's appointment as Dean at the College of Architecture and Planning as well as some of his teaching in the college. A notable file is the transcript and background on the 1989 A. Alfred Taubman Symposium on Campus Planning. During Beckley's tenure the college would be renamed as the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning. Teaching material relates to upper level studio courses and masters of urban design courses taught by Beckley.
  Note: Content relating to Beckley's tenure as dean is found within the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning records also held at the Bentley
  - A. Alfred Taubman Symposium on Campus Planning
    - Background (Box 2)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Deanship
    - Deanship and Contracts 1985-2001 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence on Appointment as Dean 1986 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence from Retirement as Dean 1997, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Course given as instructor of the "Urban Design Studio" 1986 (Box 2)
    - "Architecture: the creation of an invisible city and its artifacts", a studio held at the University of Michigan 1989 (Box 2)
  - Courses
    - 840 Urban Design Studio 1986 (Box 3)
    - ARCH 552/672 The Creation of the Invisible City and Its Artifacts 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - ARCH 552/672 Graduate Studio Campus Planning 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - "New Istanbul", Master of Urban Design Program at the University of Michigan 1998 (Box 3)
    - "Architecture 562-682", a course delivered at the College of Architecture and Urban Planning, winter 1990 (Box 3)
    - ARCH 562/632 "Woodward Light Rail Development," a physical planning studio at the College of Architecture and Urban Planning 2009, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Masters of Urban Design 722 "New Istanbul Central Business District," 2009 (Box 3)
  - Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning Space Planning Committee report 2009-2010 (Box 3)
- Genesee Institute and Genesee County Land Bank
  The Genesee Institute and Genesee County Land Bank series (0.4 linear feet, 2002-2011) contains papers relating to the role played by Beckley as a planning consultant in the creation of a land bank to assist Genesee County in developing plans for redevelopment efforts that would be generated by the Genesee County tax reversion project.
  - Contracts 2002-2005 (Box 3)
  - "Deconstructing Flint," by Wes Janz 2007 (Box 3)
  - Flint River District 2002-2010 (Box 3)
  - Genesee County Tax Reversion Project: Strategic Planning and Land Use 2002 (Box 3)
  - Managing Change draft 2010 (Box 3)
  - Mission, Board/Staff, Budget, Planning, Technical Assistance, Research 2007 (Box 3)
  - Center for Community Progress and Dissolution of Institute 2004-2011 (Box 3)
- Outsize Material
  - Awards and Citations (Box 4)
  - Student Work (Cincinnati and Harvard) (Box 4)